<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Laura and Pete's Travel blog</title>
  <link href="http://nuttall.im/chile/"/>
  <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//atom.xml"/>
  <updated>2013-01-19T00:09:14+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://nuttall.im/chile/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Pete and Laura's travel blog</name>
    <email>psn@nuttall.im</email>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//nahuel-huapi-traverse</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//nahuel-huapi-traverse.html"/>
    <title>Nahuel Huapi Traverse</title>
    <updated>2013-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We are back from the Nahuel Huapi traverse. Its been a tough six days, and now
we are completely shattered and drinking lots of water. Also everything stinks.
I have this fear we'll be kicked out of the hostel due to the smell. Here are
some notes on the route, which might be of use to others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Maps and stuff: we used the lonely planet book &lt;a
href=&quot;http://shop.lonelyplanet.com/south-america/trekking-in-the-patagonian-andes-4/&quot;&gt;Trekking
in the Patagonian Andes&lt;/a&gt;. The times in the book are
optimistic. Speculation as to why: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; The author retired from the SAS, or some other job that required running
  up hills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The author wasn't carrying a tent, food, stove, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The author was in the process of writing a book on patagonian treks and
  was therefore somewhat fitter than us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; The author had spent the past few years working as a mountain guide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I like the first theory, though the last two have the advantage of being true.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The map was kinda crappy too. Crags aren't marked. I suppose that if
you want a map with crags they start with a black bit of paper.  The nav
was pretty easy throughout the trip, but mostly because we could see the
way owing to good weather. It would be a pain to do in poor weather.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We drank the water from the rivers. It was lovely and freezing cold. We often
had our cups on the outside of our bags, and dipped them into streams. We passed
a gang of scouts singing the Spanish version of &quot;I want to go a wandering&quot;. That's
our life now. Drinking water from streams, singing kids, green trees, Lewis and
Clark wandering past, foxes barking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In less good water news, the folks down in CAB suggested added a drop of bleach
to each litre of water.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The book claims you can get food and sleep in huts known as refugios. We
shunned this option, mostly because we had the tent etc. and we didn't fancy
booking ahead. One hears mixed reports about the quality of the places, how
watertight they are etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day One&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We headed up on the ski lift from Villa Catedral (this is the primary
route in the book) mostly due to the parties of Argentine teenagers
heading for the path up to Refugio Frey. We were warned about the wind
at the bottom. It was a cold strong wind, but we were pretty stable
on our feet when we were up there. We did end up wearing thick gloves,
balaclava, many layers etc. Only one lift at the ski centre was operating,
so we took that one and had to figure out where we were at the top.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We did the traverse from the ridge above the ski center to the
turning for Refugio Frey. This is mostly over shattered rock, following
the dots. There were good views over the ridge at a low point. The turn
off to Frey (the left) and Jacob (the right) was drawn on a rock.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The book suggests dropping down to Frey, then climbing back up and down the
other side the next day. We shunned this option. It featured a pile more height
gain and loss, Megan (who we had met while white water rafting) described her
night there as an effort to hold the tent down in the wind, and we didn't fancy
hanging around with tons of teenagers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Its worth noting that the trek had quite a few parties of folk
in different levels of gear. We saw folk in trainers, without rain
protection.  Slow progress down to the valley - long scree descent. We hit
a low point when Laura stepped in someone else's poop. A shame everyone
doesn't carry a plastic trowel. Camped in the valley - its a big site
along the path. We didn't see anyone else that night, but more folks
showed up when we went to bed. In the evening, three dogs came and sniffed
around. No idea how they got into the park. It was brass monkeys in the
valley (see Committee to Ascribe a Naval Origin to Everything).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day Two&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; This was a short day - and we had hopes for day three - we pulled
out of the end of the valley and over the pass to Refugio Jakob. The
descent is more on scree fields and pretty slow. If you like walking
over shattered rock, you can do the two tops here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; When we got down to the Refugio, they said that the high route
over to  Lag Negra by Cerro Inocentes and Cerro Navidad was closed
due to snow. This led to much  griping. We wandered up to a high lake
(and wonderful corrie coated in snow) to peer at the next day's route. It
looked  good to us.  We had scanned the route with binoculars from the other side of the
valley, and were unconvinced by their concerns. We restrained ourselves
from sneaking off at 6am, and planned to do a extra day walking out and
walking in the next valley.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Day Three&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Foiled, we headed down the valley. This is a bit slow to get started, but
once over the bridge, we bombed it down the valley. Its a nice gentle
slope. However, its longer than the book says. (the book claims 13k, and
the sign at the bottom claims 18k, and the sign is a good bit closer). Its a
nice walk in the trees, but its nothing like as good as the ridge would have
been.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We hitched from the bottom almost to Colonia Suiza. As we walked
the last mile or so, we could hear a very long rock and roll guitar
solo. This kept on playing for about forever.  We pitched up at a big
camp site somewhat more used to holidaying Buenos Aries folks than smelly
hikers. I almost fainted. We ate massive burgers and drank wine. This
is the life.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day Four&lt;/h3&gt;

We were slow getting off the next day, mostly because we had lost
motivation due to the massive detour and missing out on an awesome
ridge. At least the village gave us the opportunity to get rid of rubbish
which has to be carried out. Then we picked up some left by others. It
grates on me to see such spectacular places marred by human waste. I did
jump in the lake off the pier, which was fantastic. I think we should
carry swimming stuff. The camp site showers didn't work. We ate lunch
in the town before getting back on the hoof. The walk up the valley was
hot and full of flies. There really isn't much to say about it. Just
lots of forest, lots of pesky flies, and lots of other walkers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The end of the day was probably the toughest uphill of the walk -
a 400m pull up by the waterfall. Slow slow progress with the heavy
packs. The location of La Negra refugio is fantastic. Its on the
rocks by a high lake, above a massive waterfall. The rocky sides of
Cerro Negra tower above.  We camped in a hollow in the bushes. There
were many such hollows - no one is brave enough to camp in the open. The
notorious Patagonian wind howled most of the night.
Laura shunned pasta, ate cold pizza leftover from lunch, and woke up at
4am in a hunger. Considering how bad the pasta was, this might have been
the better route. If you have suggestions of camping dinners other than
soup, pasta and sauce please send them on!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day Five&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; This was by far the best day. We went around the lake (which is harder
than it looks, and features hanging off dodgy bits of fixed rope), up to
the ridge on the far side, and along to the top of Cerro Bailey Willis
(1850m). The views from up here are fantastic. The speedy Israeli bloke
cut under the summit, and you can do that too (He seemed to do the same as
us until the top of Pico Turista, then he when back to the Refugio). We
dropped down to a col on the ridge, then headed to the top of a valley
where there is a camp site. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the first half of the day. From then on it got harder. We
headed up Pico Turista, about a 400 meters climb up a very steep scree chute. Going
was slow and unpleasant. We then went right down the other side, climbing down loose
rock. This was slow going, and the massive bags didn't help.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a slow 400m of vertical descent down to Refugio Lopez. Once there, it was about 8pm. Again we found Lonely Planetś times optimistic. The
Refugio was full of scouts. We wanted to stop here, but the book suggested
camping lower down, further from the wind and on green grass. Sadly, when we
got down to the area suggested, it was a bog. And not even a flat blog. We were
also pursued by a fox down to the area (which was maybe 200m below the Refugio
Lopez). We figured the fox wanted dinner, so we kept on moving.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


The map showed another Refugio called La Roca below
Lopez. We went down miles of 4x4 track (which was massive switchbacks)
until we turned up at a restaurant and asked for two beds and dinner. The
Netherlands-Argentine couple explained it was a restaurant and had
never heard of the mythical La Roca refugio. We were persuaded to eat
but as it got darker fortunately they allowed us to camp outside the
restaurant which we very much appreciated. There was a great view
and no electricity. The waitress told us what food they had and we
ordered almost all of it. The hunger had set in. Four empanadas, a pie,
a pizza and a salad, followed by dessert. She said &quot;wow you are really
hungry!&quot; We explained we had been walking for 5 days. And 12 hours of walking, a tough day.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Day Six&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We had coffee and a chat with the restaurant owners which was
interesting.  It turns out that only about 30% of Argentines have
official jobs and pay tax.  Most don't have bank accounts. We then
walked out along the switchbacks - this wasn't far, but we don't know
how far - and back to Colonia Suiza. Laura saw Magellanic woodpeckers
along the way. We aimed to appear on ruta 79 as close to Colonia Suiza
as possible, and we popped out on a road with private property notices
all over it. Oops. No one hassled us. The bus back to Bariloche was the
final straw - we waited 50 minutes past the time, then got lunch, then
went back and waited some more, all with no sign of the bus. In the end
we got a taxi. And then steak. Massive steak. We wore the same clothes
for 5 and half days and we are sorry for whoever washed them for us.  &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//glacier</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//glacier.html"/>
    <title>I asked for ice, but this is ridiculous</title>
    <updated>2013-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; We have seen glaciers before. I think the first time for me was in
Canada. We visited a closed viewpoint in Banff national park. We waded
though waist deep snow to peer down on a very blue lake and the grey ice
below. Snow was all around, and heavy clouds hung over us. The white of
the snow and the grey of the rock is all I recall seeing of the glacier
and the ice field beyond. It was cold.  We had a way to drive before
night and snow fall. The first time Laura tried to turn the car, it
slid off the snow covered road and into a gentle snowbank.  We turned
away from the glacier. Perhaps its more spectacular in summertime, when,
you know, its actually open for viewing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; School had a photo of a glacier in France. It looks muddy and was
a odd grey-brown colour. Each year a field trip visited it. School had
a collection of photos taken from  the same spot, year after year. Each
year it had retreated many meters.  These days I assume the glacier has
retreated out of shot. One day it will be gone altogether. Needless to
say, this makes me a bit sad.  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt; Perito Moreno is nothing like these. A massive white wall of ice
advancing over the valley, it seems otherworldly. It is impossible to
fit it all in. Behind the leading wall, the glacier and the ice field
behind it stretch to the horizon. Up close, one watches spires of ice
fall silently until they hit the water. The boom of impact echoes from
the mountains. Enormous cracking noises, like a giant standing on a frozen
sea, come from deep within the glacier as it crawls forward. Icebergs bob
in the milky water. Semi circles of ice come out from the edge - marking
places where the glacier has calved off more chunks.  Peering into the
cracks, one sees a deep blue white colour, suggesting a impossible maze
of chasms and fractures.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt; The glacier has crawled down out of the Andes. It has hit two
problems - a mountain, and a large river. The glacier crawls out into
the river. After many months, it reaches the other side and blocks
the river. Neither the ice nor the water can erode the mountain fast
enough. The water level rises until the pressure undercuts the glacier,
leading the river to flow under an arch in the ice.  After yet more time,
the arch, worn by the water and pressured by the weight of the ice,
cracks and explodes, leaving the river to run free once more.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The only way of fully understanding the size of the glacier is
to take to the air.  The mountain, bigger than anything in Ireland,
in barely noticeable in the pictures. The river, large enough to have
a detachment of the Argentine navy (no, I don't know why or what they
were doing), shrinks on the postcard. The glacier, miles of cracks and
wrinkles covering its surface, looks like a unstoppable force, sent down
from the Andes to march, Sherman like, over the Patagonian steppe.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Anyway. We have no photos because this whole town
gets it's internet by encoding bits into icebergs floating down &lt;a
href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentino_Lake&quot;&gt;Argentino
  Lake&lt;/a&gt;
. The acks come back in the tourist copies of &lt;i&gt;In Patagonia&lt;/i&gt;. If
you think the Mylodon is a metaphor for Chatwin's sanity, you are carrying a
1.
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//white-water-rafting</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//white-water-rafting.html"/>
    <title>White water rafting</title>
    <updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; Hello folks, Laura here. As promised, a few details about this
excellent day out over a week ago. We went with Extremo Sur and highly
recommend them. It was so much fun. We went up a valley to a farm
where we got changed into wetsuits and the rest of the gear. Then it
was down to the R&amp;iacute;o Manso Inferior (river) for a safety talk and
then we were off. It was utterly superb and I didn't want it to end.
The river is stunning - clear water, high cliffs, wonderful forest and
views of mountain ridges. And the excellent rapids. I have always been
hopeless at water sports and could just about swim across a river but we
had an excellent guide and I loved it. We went in for an (intentional)
swim twice. The swimming position is on your back with your backside
lowered and the water carries you along. All good things come to an end
and when we came out of the river we headed up to the border with Chile
and then past a customs office and back to the farm for an &lt;i&gt;asado&lt;/i&gt;
which was excellent. We had some good chat with an Australian girl and
two Argentinians who wanted to know lots about Ireland and the UK and
what we thought of Argentina.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ApdsYvXB9y6LJstNRQb_We7tUZUDEQvmLBkenVWBi7o?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ZRtSwghpcCk/UPM0F6pjwnI/AAAAAAAAKac/11lpDiIoyyM/s400/DSC_0062.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;266&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;



  &lt;a  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/hWzcQ-cOcU4pEAj2N21rju7tUZUDEQvmLBkenVWBi7o?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-RSLyVmr0qBw/UPM5P4BWyMI/AAAAAAAAKb4/y3eoEUWlCgk/s400/DSC_0113.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;266&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/WhiteWaterRafting?authuser=0&amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCNSl0Nul25GrqwE&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;The whole album.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//bariloche</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//bariloche.html"/>
    <title>Into 2013, Bariloche</title>
    <updated>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; We are in Bariloche in the Lakes
District of Argentina. This is supposed to be where &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/features/4170977/Did-Nazi-Adolf-Hitler-live-to-old-age-in-Bariloche-Argentina.html&quot;&gt;Hitler
Retired&lt;/a&gt;. I've guessed this from the title and cover of a Spanish book
in a shop earlier this week. The guy knows how to pick a good spot - this
is the Argentinian Switzerland. It's all very alpine, there are lots
of wooden buildings, good chocolate and even &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.toytowngermany.com/lofi/index.php/t48124.html&quot;&gt;rodelbahns&lt;/a&gt;.  Laura points
out how you just cant get away from Hitler. I point out how you've imagined
an evil dictator on a small wheeled cart going down a hill.  Possibly we
need to spend more time in Germany.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; That sun article reminds me of the tale of &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Hitler's+one+man+invasion+of+Scotland%3B+FACE-TO-FACE+WITH+EVIL%3A...-a060433070&quot;&gt;
Hitler's visit to Knoydart.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The journey here has been pretty good, and we haven't had time to
update the blog much. We left Arica in the far north of Chile on the 26th,
and took a 40 hour bus journey - interrupted by a quick curry in the nicest
Indian restaurant in Santiago. We then missed our bus from Santiago to
Temuco, but Turbus put us on the next bus that evening. You might think
that missing a connection would be a pain - and 40 hours on a bus would
be the sort of thing the CIA would do to Pakistani teenagers, but you'd
be wrong. Chilean buses (we've mostly gone with turbus) are cheap and
comfortable, and the company doesn't gouge stranded travellers. Chile
has better public transport than the UK. If we had only deported &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augusto_Pinochet&quot;&gt;Pinochet&lt;/a&gt;,
  they might let us in on the secret.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The only unnerving thing about the journey was that just before we went to
sleep, the conductor asked for our passports. He then pocketed them. Que
freak out. Que farcical conversation with minimal shared language asking
what he was doing.  Identity theft? Crazy Chilean laws? A man explained
that it was the law and everyone else handed theirs over and we got them
back in the morning. On another internal bus we had our bags searched at
a check point. Another oddity is that at Arica you have to buy a platform
ticket from a special ticket office in order to get onto the platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Temuco is a nice town - with real coffee and excellent chocolate
(Cassis in the mall which is very European in appearance). Unfortunately
we suffered from pickpocketing in the bus terminal only 2 minutes after
arriving.  The reason we were there was to rent a car. At this point,
having rented in Norway, the US, Canada and Argentina, we expect to at
some stage to go to Turkey and have a conversation like this:

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Me: we're thinking about driving over the border into Afghanistan, then
smuggling raw sewage cross country while being shot at by the Taliban. What do
you have?
Car rental: how about this Nissan Micra?
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Anyway, First car rental lent us a really nice clean car that we
knocked around, bottomed out on a dirt road and covered in dust. Not
too bad on the scale of things. Also, it was a relief to see water,
grass and trees after all that time in the desert. It's very different
to when we were last in Argentina, cooler, greener, a bit richer and no
more need for the clay dome-shaped ovens outside peoples houses. The
cars are just as battered and the meat just as tasty.  Another thing
we have noticed about the Argentinian people, and to some extent the
Chileans, is the importance of family. Everyone talks about their family
and we even saw a parade which was a celebration of an extended family.
Driving in Chile was much easier than in Argentina due to road markings
and less recklessness from other drivers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

We drove into the shadow of the volcano at Conguillio national park. The
volcano last erupted over new year in 2008 - everyone had to be evacuated
and it left areas of the park devastated. The roads are lined with
warning signs, volcano traffic lights, and the odd helipad.  We were
in the land of the Mapuche people (who have had a hard time of it) and
whole forests of Araucaria trees (monkey puzzle). It was spectacular. We
camped in the park over new year.  To anyone thinking about going the
camping is expensive but it's a nice site with lots of hot water. Once
there, we tramped up into the woods on the start of a traverse of the
mountains. Sadly, to get to the top of the traverse one needs tons of
gear that that we were not carrying. Also, the area for camping along
the traverse had the biggest, hairiest spiders we've ever seen - sleep
would have been a challenge.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/_suHMHOKMeUqYnDjEY7rftMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-POmMPthlFTE/UOm-BLkW3eI/AAAAAAAAJ8M/iL9vjJBVvi8/s400/P1020837.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rPT3Zg9btgRgXun3yscQR9MTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-SSMVyzUcF80/UOm7nBCIMiI/AAAAAAAAJ64/kDggsWW-b_0/s400/P1020819.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/2wb31hLyrhUPCErTfcczcNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-S3zEQU_ZrMk/UOm9_xidkoI/AAAAAAAAJ8E/wik3Nwi4cJg/s400/P1020832.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/BF02c9VxPse7IORNWtM6fNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-UTnlUx1ZwYM/UOm6053530I/AAAAAAAAJ6g/yEFojpZMNpg/s400/P1020815.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;

The next day we tromped up the lava field. This is our third valle de la
luna/valley of the moon. The volcanic ash and lava looks and feels like snow.
Laura disagrees. Its not clear what she disagrees with, but she put her
disagreement in. Anyway. The only life is small lizards and insects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Laura: it looks nothing like the photos
Pete: perhaps the photos predate the eruption
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/cJMyk46MoIDVuXGenaf8itMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ZvTlQ8vuigo/UOnLd68T03I/AAAAAAAAKCY/TWeQt31Vkbk/s400/P1050852.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/MbLSwnPD0Am2WRlR2pl11dMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-0TUV7pBZX_Q/UOnK2NMp7NI/AAAAAAAAKB8/YtSsDQOGNfU/s400/P1050809.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rFyOwAg-qMVCVIXL1-UWYdMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-lSc4ZdVQdpE/UOnArPOhCsI/AAAAAAAAJ9s/4vdGgHlnOts/s400/P1020898.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/2EYcBziMZ1uzCp57YRJ2NtMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-2lbMMOfKXUU/UOnK2BzXsyI/AAAAAAAAKCA/QNk2NlF52Dc/s400/P1050838.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;

On news year's day we floated around the local lake on a boat. The first time we
tried to hire a boat, we got it into the water, and it leaked. It leaked like a
waterfall. We went back the next day, and had a great time visiting empty
beaches, isolated waterfalls, and so on. Also, its time for this video. (Thanks
Jen!)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ry0Bv1HQRD4&quot;
  frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/lxE94xklj6isFm3Hm8q6F9MTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-p3ZrUXOPTGk/UOnMEstbfhI/AAAAAAAAKCs/HL3L3D-x4oE/s400/P1050890.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xVdZB7r4sFxjK73Q8E5fvNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-b-pWLdNN_uc/UOnNrG4Bt9I/AAAAAAAAKD0/4asNaYAw0xY/s400/P1050924.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;
  After our stay in Conguillio National Park we headed out for some cheaper
  camping in Melipeuco and found a gem of a place. Turismo Relmucura - camping
  and a dinner with two glasses of wine for about 20 sterling. The host was
  very welcoming and gave us dinner in her house with a view of the volcano. We
  got to eat pino&amp;ntilde;es, the pine nuts of the Araucaria tree. Cake, chocolate
  and costs (including fuel - the fuel filling man laughed at Laura´s bunch of
  notes) have all improved on the journey south.
  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We jumped on the bus down to Puerto Varas - which
is very German. There are two German schools and you can buy k&amp;uuml;chen and
apfelstrudel as well as empanadas. The next day we headed though the &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.crucedelagos.com/&quot;&gt;Cruce De Lagos&lt;/a&gt; to Argentina. We
were sad to be leaving Puerto Varas, and there is lots to come back
for. This is the old road, featuring 4 buses and three boats. We were
a bit nervous about it, since it looks more like a old person thing
to do. We got on the bus and it was full of older, somewhat richer,
people. They were also people who were staying in a place with a good
shower. Things got off to a rough start as we were some of the last
people to get on board, and folks weren't willing to share their second
seat. Its hard to tell if this was a possible smell or just being &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://theoatmeal.com/comics/airplane_heard&quot;&gt;grabby.&lt;/a&gt; We jumped off at some waterfalls,
and everyone got in a neat queue for tickets (apart from the possibly-smelly
heroes of this blog, who had a empanada. (side note, this was the first
breakfast that wasn't bread and cheese or muesli and water for a while).
Breakfast here is poor - white bread with jam or cheese is standard. Fortunately
in Bariloche I had a bacon omelette.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The falls in Parque Nacional Vicente Pe&amp;#341;ez Rosales were kinda British -
there were tons of people, there were safety fences, someone came over
and complained about Laura standing on a rock. Laura then insisted on
rocking a bench.


&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/nqMOOAnnPbnUNSNvhGrkF9MTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-CUgDkTxp57k/UOm1oLvNg_I/AAAAAAAAJ5A/ePBOzRQVFr0/s400/P1020962.JPG&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/0OsjUu6N13sUkAFi_4JUzNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-1RjmoEhUkjA/UOm09GOC65I/AAAAAAAAJ4s/CDArpF3J7b8/s400/P1020946.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; You just gotta fight the man. The first boat had great views, though
it was a bit full of people. Annoying people. I've noticed that men
(and it is normally men) like carrying big cameras on these sorts of
trips. I like to imagine that there's a pecking order going on, and the
guy with the most camera gear is the alpha male of the pack.  His genes
and opinions on gear are spread widely. From time to time, a challenger
rises. One this boat the fight was between a guy those camera lens was
longer that my arm, and another guy who had two massive SLRs.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/aPT3xs6a5I0FnRSFlEG5VtMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-lE5LPzibBtM/UOmnuwWQGrI/AAAAAAAAJzE/x0XiPgFOE9I/s400/P1030007.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rm_zhLShV49ZRRurpMYjkdMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-2dnsWn52E0s/UOmoQA3UeXI/AAAAAAAAJzQ/StyKtss2d_A/s400/P1030010.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We got to a tiny village at the far end of the lake, and everyone mercifully
wandered off. Wandering was helped by the descent of horseflies the size
of bumblebees. These can bite. If you want to experience a bit of South America
without leaving your sofa, squeeze the flesh on your arm with pliers until you
draw blood. Thats what it feels like. Laura claims they can bite though
clothing.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We did go ziplining through the trees, and watched a few birds. Zip
lining is great fun. We should do more of that. The lake was massive,
and the locals own boats rather than cars since there are no roads. The
boat's handy public address system told us that the boat takes the local
kids to and from boarding school on Monday and Friday. Finding ourselves
on that sailing might have been worse than a pile of Americans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, after more boat and bus trips, we made it to Argentina. Highlights
including Mount Tronador, which is covered in glaciers, and people feeding the
gulls off the back of the boat.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Jw3gI00nBM7Rpmyz6LP-nNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vEcNVmCiDHA/UOmp-gPQN1I/AAAAAAAAJ0o/Bmd-gOTyLvg/s400/P1030081.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Iao0D8ygqUkYoSeZ3O9JXtMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-lfgyJDTiTk0/UOmsWc739AI/AAAAAAAAJ08/JslfCCUBE5U/s400/P1030115.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/586f7Qso0vAhjSRqhyXXlNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4yjukkj55N0/UOmyFbX626I/AAAAAAAAJ3c/HBOGg8WUBmo/s400/P1030212.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/l7QFq0CHFg4Ha_1_OVAq2NMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-NxssO8D8QFM/UOmuDtSmRkI/AAAAAAAAJ1s/Eeipx0006UA/s400/P1030133.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;


I recall hearing a story that the Brits fighting in 1982 were surprised
by the skill and lack of fear and common sense of the Argentinian
pilots. These are the same talents one needs to cross the road here. You
have to walk out and hope someone stops.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Since I've mentioned the war, Lonely planet's history of Argentina takes a
certain amount of glee over the abilities of the army. It turns out that
experience in seizing power, machine gunning thousands of dissidents, and
burying them in ditches does not translate to being good at fighting someone
else with guns. While I'm rambling - that bit of Fawlty Towers nails the
British attitude to the other war. Props to John Cleese et al (Who wrote  the script
anyway?). It would have been so easy for them to take the mickey out of the
Germans. Anyway.

&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;

Since we need dollars for a hotel in Buenos Aires and it is impossible to lay
your hands on them in Argentina, we exchanged some Chilean pesos into dollars in
Temuco. The first place quoted us about twice the normal rate. We just walked
out. The second place was about what we expected. The need for dollars is
because no one trusts the Argentinian Peso - or the Argentinian banks. We pay in
cash for anything smaller than a flight. Chile, of course, is also mad. They
have changed all the phone numbers, and no one can make a phone call. Other
things we haven´t quite got used to is no plates for eating bread and a chaotic
approach to queuing!
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;

Yesterday we went white water rafting and it was so much fun. More on that
another time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we are almost caught up on this thing, and its getting late,
so thats about it. We have ticked over the half way point, and the end
is in sight.Yeah, we are sad about this. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos: &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/CampingInConguillioNationalPark#&quot;&gt;Camping
  in Conguilla National Park&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/TheRoadToBariloche&quot;&gt;Road
  to Bariloche&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//meths</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//meths.html"/>
    <title>The fuel saga</title>
    <updated>2013-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have been having a long yak shave over camping fuel. We didn't
bring any as airlines frown on carrying it. Lonely planet tells horror
stories of airlines throwing out stoves altogether. We have a  &lt;a
  href=&quot;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trangia&quot;&gt;Trangia&lt;/a&gt;. It burns &lt;a
href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Methylated_spirit&quot;&gt;meths&lt;/a&gt;.
This is nearly pure alcohol. If it was pure, it would be odourless and
colourless. And drunks would drink it.  Most countries, including the UK,
insist on it having an added smell and colour, and be made undrinkable. Of
course, every country picks its own colour.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We knew all this because at some stage, dad had bought some in Norway (where its
called Rod spirit). The bottle came back half full, and when I went on DoE, I
took the rod spirit along to finish off. The teacher running the trip sniffed
the bottle, peered at the red liquid, and declared it not to be meths. I pointed
out it was Norwegian, hence the funny characters, and it burnt like meths. I came
home from the trip with half a bottle of British meths and half a bottle of rod
spirit. My dad was not pleased. However, it could have gone worse - if I had
pointed out to the teacher that rod spirit was alcohol.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the time, I figured this was  some sort of metaphor for the DoE scheme - how
the scheme had been corrupted into some sort of rule following exercise, and so
on and so forth. These days, I figure the old Duke would be proud of the
teachers knee jerk rejection of anything foreign.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to 2013 (a quick hi there to the woman on Amtrak who told me that the world
would end in 2012. She was completely straight faced). Finding meths in Chile
wasn't so bad - we asked in an outdoor store (which was useless, rant about that
coming) and they directed us to the local hardware store. The guy there
tolerated our Spanish (he must have been the one guy in San Pedro who didn't work
in the tourism industry) and sold us a bottle. We filled up our fuel bottle, and
left the remainder with the hostel owner in Arica. He was happy to get some
&quot;People are always asking me where to get this!&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That was the start of the odyssey. When we showed up in Bariloche, we figured
buying more fuel (the Chilean stuff burnt hot but quickly, and we needed more)
would be easy. We are in a hiking capital of the world, right? How hard can it
be?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Turns out that the walking stores around here are mostly useless
unless you want to buy clothes. No idea why. However, one shop assistant
pointed us to the good store, where among fishing poles, guns, and
actually useful gear, we managed to buy some stuff. They didn't have fuel,
and were possibly the first place to mention MSR (so many places thought
we wanted MSR that I considered getting a tshirt. &quot;No. I don't want MSR,
thanks for asking&quot;). The local hardware store sold us universal solvente
- no idea what it is yet. The internet turned up a list of names used in
Argentina. The local pharmacy recognized one of them, and pointed us to a
small supermarket selling nothing but cleaning products.  There, in among
the hairspray and the toilet roll, we found our fuel. The guy there asked
if it was for fondue. Told you this place was like Switzerland.  &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//birds-of-arica</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//birds-of-arica.html"/>
    <title>Birds of Arica</title>
    <updated>2012-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; After a relaxing Christmas swimming and body boarding, we are heading
south at last. Next stop Temuco - we get there on the 28th. We have had enough
of deserts and high altitudes and its time to start walking. Somewhat
better news is that we have &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/BirdsOfArica?authuser=0&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;photos
      from Arica&lt;/a&gt; on the web. A selection is below. For Christmas dinner
    we had a barbecue - it was remarkably tasty.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/J8hYMt8HYFHcZoo6XlrTFNMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-vOOB8nAORRQ/UNkPMXLjLQI/AAAAAAAAJtI/0NTzSHSjXrY/s400/P1050726.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/5CDPcFZWFgO3aLlBrScv2NMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-iyAj6og1lK8/UNkLGLCelbI/AAAAAAAAJpk/bS140AZGXng/s400/P1020463.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/c0gpsKG1Db-653eCgB1n_tMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-p9Ugp6IRCLM/UNkN69lRzcI/AAAAAAAAJsQ/DM4dSi6zm3s/s400/P1020642.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/YA3g8TryHkKUayKT0k4WCtMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-lK276RLYD1A/UNkMNf3iBgI/AAAAAAAAJqM/Xetu7V_H-ug/s400/P1020761.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//christmas-eve</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//christmas-eve.html"/>
    <title>Christmas eve</title>
    <updated>2012-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We are still in Arica, and will be here until the 26th. We've been out to swim
in the sea and watch the local wildlife - one of these is not a normal Christmas
activity. The plan for tomorrow is more of the same, with a barbecue for
Christmas dinner.

  &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//ssl</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//ssl.html"/>
    <title>Nerd updates</title>
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; &lt;b&gt;Nerdy content&lt;/b&gt; I made a few changes to the blog. I have moved
  the URL to &lt;a href=&quot;www.nuttall.im&quot;&gt;www.nuttall.im&lt;/a&gt;, rather than
  http://nuttall.im/chile/. There
was  not anything interesting on / anyway. I should have got mod_rewrite
  to do the correct rewriting, but if a url is broken for you - or
something is broken for you - let me know at psn _at_ nuttall.im.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've moved to SSL and &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_Strict_Transport_Security&quot;&gt;STS&lt;/a&gt;.
    The long term goal for ssl is either to set up &lt;a
    href=&quot;http://antony.lesuisse.org/software/ajaxterm/&quot;&gt;ajaxterm&lt;/a&gt;
  or similar, or to play around with &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://www.chromium.org/spdy&quot;&gt;spdy.&lt;/a&gt; I would like ajaxterm
as a backup for putty in internet cafes, and I want to play around with
spdy anyway. STS protects against &lt;a
    href=&quot;http://www.thoughtcrime.org/software/sslstrip/&quot;&gt;sslstrip&lt;/a&gt;,
        and also does a better job
at flushing out mixed content warnings.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imperialviolet.org/2012/07/19/hope9talk.html&quot;&gt;Adam
Langley's blog&lt;/a&gt; is pretty good at explaining what to do. I got the
certs off &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.startssl.com/&quot;&gt;startssl&lt;/a&gt; - who were
  puzzled by an Argentinian IP and Dublin
address and wanted to ask more questions. They were convinced
by a Google maps photo of the roof of my block of flats. &lt;a
href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Trouble_with_Trillions&quot;&gt;Ob
Simpson's reference.&lt;/a&gt; I also screwed up serving the certs with Apache
- and didn't send the full chain. This broke Firefox, but not chrome. Problem
    found by my Dad and reproduced with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=nuttall.im&quot;&gt;ssllabs test thingo.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found one problem with ssl - &lt;a
href=&quot;http://disqus.com/&quot;&gt;disqus&lt;/a&gt;
broke. It fetched a resource over http. The Google suggested turning
off their 2012 update. It seems to work after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added the www subdomain so I could scope cookies to www.nuttall.im, not
  nuttall.im. I'm not doing much with cookies, so I might change that back.&lt;/p&gt;


</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//arcia</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//arcia.html"/>
    <title>Arica</title>
    <updated>2012-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some non-nerdy content: we are in &lt;a
href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arica&quot;&gt;Arica&lt;/a&gt;, right at
the top of Chile. The hope had been to spend Christmas in  &lt;a
href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lauca_National_Park&quot;&gt;Lauca National
Park&lt;/a&gt;, but we haven't had any success hiring a car. We might spend
Christmas here, eating barbecue and sitting on the beach. This idea is
growing on me.

&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//bolivia</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//bolivia.html"/>
    <title>Bolivia</title>
    <updated>2012-12-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; Hello folks, it´s Laura here. On Monday we left San Pedro for
the altiplano of Bolivia. We went with Cordillera Traveller and can
recommend them, we had a great Bolivian guide. The border crossing is
the most remote we have ever seen.  Shortly after the border we crossed
into Reserva Nacional de Fauna Andina Eduardo Avaroa which is very rich
in minerals and has isolated communtities of indigenous people living in
harsh and isolated conditions. We stopped at several lakes and a pool
heated by hot springs which was lovely even though it was thundering
and hailing when we were in it. We stopped at Geyser Sol de Manaña.
It was steaming away furiously. I couldn´t go close to it because of the
sulphur but Pete´s lungs are stronger and he got some photos. The most
impressive lake was Laguna Colorada, a Ramsar site which is red due to the
pigments contained in algae present there. There were lots of flamingoes,
mostly Andean but also Chilean and Puna/James flamingoes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/lz-HIRylOluT-LFnbV0Z_H4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uA42iOxd3Cw/UNSREdlm28I/AAAAAAAAJXY/feZO_rST9U4/s400/P1020007.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/pI65gpwhdWpS77zjXuSVBn4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-OJT_izBNS_0/UNSDsbmJ7dI/AAAAAAAAJRE/fj7pOyYCdXA/s400/P1050518.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the duration of the trip we were on dirt roads in a 4x4 and at 3600-4900m
altitude. We have never been anywhere so remote. The wildlife and scenery are
spectacular. The first night was spent at a small dwelling in the middle of
nowhere´at 4200m. We slept reasonably considering the altitude. On the second
day we stopped at more lakes and interesting rock formations. One of the rock
sights was depressing, lots of cans, rubbish and toilet roll strewn around from
previous groups. It seems that unless bins and toilets are provided in every
corner of the Earth that humans reach there will always be some idiots who ruin
places with rubbish.  We broke down twice but after the fuel filter had been
cleaned the trusty Toyota carried us on to San Juan a small settlement at 3600m
where we spent the night in a salt hostel.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/EmpTztpKUf3ujL44H1z0M34FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GlQZsav5QL8/UNSUWYmneyI/AAAAAAAAJcc/XyfLYp9BwrU/s400/P1020163.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/qy0a28hFRE2ym93P0aYX2H4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-UxjkzWxdy_Y/UNR-LLF7Q5I/AAAAAAAAJOo/LrS01LdARcw/s400/P1050612.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/s9TfAand-CGeGPfPMgTwEX4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-l1yQJdDhPn4/UNSRmVKgTqI/AAAAAAAAJYA/FXQNFJ4nac8/s400/P1020050.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/iUJeYbgBlz5elCSUfkwKFn4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-qw4opw6PoNA/UNSC1IYo-BI/AAAAAAAAJVA/yzS7_Zctcyc/s400/P1050486.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the third day we drove on to the Salar de Uyuni, an amazing salt flat which
is the world´s largest at 10,582 square km.  The elevation is about 3600m and in
places the salt is 150m deep. In the rainy season it floods and is impassable.
In summer there can be water close to the surface so a good guide is needed to
avoid falling through. Our guide explained to us that the Salar rises by about
5cm every year, but the process was lost on me due to not understanding enough
Spanish. It is also the largest source of Lithium in the world and some salt is
harvested by locals. The next stop was the train cemetry on the outskirts of the
town of Uyuni. This was thoroughly depressing, the land around the town is
covered in rubbish and it is grim. We passed a night there in a basic hotel due
to trouble at the border. The indigenous people of Reserva Nacional de Fauna
Andina Eduardo Avaroa are due 10% of the profits from tourism but they have not
received it from the Government for one and a half years, so they are striking
and blocking all access to the reserve. Hopefully they will get the money soon.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/vp_TAanChkvzO6qrF-VYVn4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ZyhwwzbGveI/UNR-ilcHweI/AAAAAAAAJPA/BatOXtH7eI4/s400/P1050648.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/cn4n9BBEsS3q-SQt28VR_n4FfsMlZknWAM8paGx5dLE?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-LytDqVB5XvE/UNSVqP7fgTI/AAAAAAAAJd0/_sRv0vOIs6g/s400/P1020218.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On Thursday we rose at 5am for the transfer to another border. It was a long, hot
and uncomfortable day. We had to pay 15 Bolivianos to leave the country and then
we waited around for a couple of hours for a minibus from Chile to collect us.
We´re glad to be back on paved roads.


&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/Bolivia?authuser=0&amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCOHl8qPpo8zmrgE&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;the
  album.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//san-pedro-again</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//san-pedro-again.html"/>
    <title>Around San Pedro de Atacama</title>
    <updated>2012-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; We are still in San Pedro de Atacama, after several great days. We
have seen geysers, swam in hot springs, watched flamingoes and other
high altitude birds, toured ruins, and marvelled at the landscape. We
have avoided the local minefield.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The El Tatio geysers are at about 4200 meters, and the best time to see them is
at dawn. The option we picked was to get on a tour bus at 4am. It was -5 degrees
C when we arrived. The crazy option was to camp up there. The reason for the
early start is that they are at their most impressive with cold air. Of course,
it warms up fast....
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The geysers are really impressive. Bubbling mud, towers of steam, and fantastic
colours. They come from a underground river from Bolivia which touches magma.
When the water reaches the surface it is 85 degrees C. We heard some horror
stories about people straying away from the paths and falling through fragile
crust and others going too close for the perfect photo, falling in and later
dying from the burns. Thankfully everyone in our group understood that the walls
meant go no further. I'm hoping the photos come out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/KVoWrnfE_QDwTg7Ze9k27lBkyxbwgklftcdC3Fi_vXs?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-nJETJai-DN0/UM4triP-wHI/AAAAAAAAI-c/lq_IbOMz5uU/s400/P1010635.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/pVUxEUe1aGOy0KeOKyDfklBkyxbwgklftcdC3Fi_vXs?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-fYodMsjOPyA/UM4txbFoNDI/AAAAAAAAI-k/ByTeM244TTE/s400/P1010653.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have been to see two archaeological sites built by the Atacame&amp;ntilde;o People - mostly
the remains of buildings preserved for hundreds of years by the desert. The
local museum has many of the objects found - and is excellent. Pukara de Quitor
has many walls up a slope - the last stand of the locals when the Spanish showed
up. Aldea de Tulor is the remains of a two thousand year old village. Its mostly
buried in sand to keep it out of the wind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/-frM_6bX1cbLuParQpbfE1BkyxbwgklftcdC3Fi_vXs?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-nKcXlTcMK9g/UM3qZLqvOnI/AAAAAAAAI4c/TMNrFHLLUR0/s400/P1050405.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We been floating in Laguna Cejar - a salt lagoon!  Its 30 metres deep but you can't
drown. The water is  denser than people. Its lovely and relaxing. When
you get out and dry off you become covered in a crust of salt! We enjoyed
it so much that we might go again if time permits.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Gw0ukLCYRvALWk8K1FQu51BkyxbwgklftcdC3Fi_vXs?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-urBw7lSd8T8/UM4uX65Q6gI/AAAAAAAAI_Q/f1gTygSvxJc/s400/P1010917.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was saying the desert was somewhat green. Biking and travelling around shows
the green to be the local oasis. Beyond there, its a barren arid landscape. What
bushes there are only grow when there is rain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We went to a high altitude lake  - Salar de Tara - where there were thousands of flamingoes, with the snow
capped Andes of Bolivia behind. A wonderful sight.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/LwI8hikLCcyloczNnRmAlVBkyxbwgklftcdC3Fi_vXs?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-rDGhl3DlMlw/UM4s_Jt5dMI/AAAAAAAAI9k/bRqbMOJIQ7k/s400/P1010326.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
On Monday we are heading to Bolivia for 4 days to see the largest salt flat in
the world among other things. Then we'll be back in San Pedro for a night and
then it's the night bus to Arica, the northernmost town in Chile. From there we
hope to go to Lauca National Park and maybe we'll be camping there over
Christmas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/SanPedro?authuser=0&amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCMnalJOztq-EFA&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;The
  album&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/BirdsOfTheAndes?authuser=0&amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCM7LjbHki8zYhAE&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;Birds.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//civil-rights-captcha</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//civil-rights-captcha.html"/>
    <title>Civil rights Captcha</title>
    <updated>2012-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Warning - nerdy content&lt;/b&gt; I spent a lazy afternoon back in Dublin
pulling apart Civil rights captcha, and I wanted to save my notes by
sticking them on the blog.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Civil rights captcha is a system that aims to educate people on civil rights as
well as tell humans from robots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/&quot;&gt;The site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2012/10/empathy-captcha/&quot;&gt;Wired article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4619248&quot;&gt;Hacker news thread&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that wired and therefore hacker news talk about filtering out internet
idiots with this, which isn't mentioned on their site.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;how secure is this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; First idea - they only have a few questions. I think each question
takes a human to come up with it and review it.They can't really raise
civil rights awareness with a incorrect collection of ills and they
don't want to be sued for libel.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Download the page 1000 times.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
for x in {0..1000}; do
  curl -s -o dataset/$x captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org
  done
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Compare them to one another.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
for x in dataset/*; do
  diff dataset/0 $x | egrep '&gt;'
done | sort | uniq &gt; questions
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They have given 8 questions. Theories as to why:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they only have 8 questions.&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;they shard questions by IP or user agent. For example, they might
  only give curl users 8 questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
They might also have many correct answers per question. With a normal captcha you
only have one correct answer.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
How many answers are there? Use chrome to grab a image url. Use curl to hit that
url a few times. Each file has a different sha1sum (it would be nice to have a
command line tool that uses a cheaper hash), so possibly a bug in the
loop or a different image. Download 1000 images.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
mkdir images
for x in {0..10000}; do
  curl -s -o images/$x 'http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/captchaAPI/securimage_show.php?sid=xJZNm2G1mK5TQQH69mX3&amp;newset=7&amp;lang=en';
done
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hash all the images, see 1003 different hashes. Ideas:
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;different words&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;different lines over each word.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some sort of salting in the image to defeat hashing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bug in the loop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
Look at the images. Lots of different words, some negative, some positive. Some
dupe words, but not many. Download 6k images. All of them are different.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;

Peer at chrome's debugger. Watch the process. The javascript fetches one image with
newset=1, and two more without the newset parameter. Each request has
a sid parameter set to a random string. The random string is different
for each image. The newset request sets a cookie, which is sent back to
the server. Example cookie:

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
Set-Cookie: PHPSESSID=eq0llt1rjtfr0h3fa0mlorrm67; path=/
&lt;/pre&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
Random string notes: its not clear what purpose the random string serves. If I
had to guess, it prevents http caching.
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
Once the user enters a answer, it does validation with a request like so.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
curl --cookie 'PHPSESSID=e66bfeidg9ukm1ovvk9cn1i8f6'
'http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/captchaAPI/?callback=jQuery1&amp;code=concerned'
&lt;/pre&gt;


result:

&lt;pre&gt;
jQuery1({&quot;answer&quot;:&quot;false&quot;});
&lt;/pre&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
So it presumably stores a map of session to correct answer on the server side,
and returns a json blob if the user's input is correct.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code for a session&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
set -eux
session_id=$RANDOM
dir=session-$session_id
mkdir $dir
random=$(printf &quot;%06daaaaaaaaaaaaaa&quot; $session_id)
curl -s -o $dir/1.png --dump-header $dir/1.headers
&quot;http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/captchaAPI/securimage_show.php?sid=${random}&amp;newset=1&amp;lang

cookie=$(awk '/Set-Cookie:/{print $2}' session/1.headers | tr -d ';')
awk '/Set-Cookie:/{print $2}' $dir/1.headers
curl --cookie &quot;$cookie&quot; -s -o $dir/2.png --dump-header $dir/2.headers &quot;http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/captchaAPI/securimage_show.php?sid=${ra
curl --cookie &quot;$cookie&quot; -s -o $dir/3.png --dump-header $dir/3.headers &quot;http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/captchaAPI/securimage_show.php?sid=${ra

echo $dir
echo 'work out the answer'
read answer

curl -s --dump-header $dir/answer.headers --cookie &quot;$cookie&quot; &quot;http://captcha.civilrightsdefenders.org/captchaAPI/?callback=jQuery1&amp;code=${answer}&quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Can this be brute forced?&lt;/h3&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
Start out by sending the contents of /usr/share/dict/british-english
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
% wc -l /usr/share/dict/british-english
99156 /usr/share/dict/british-english
&lt;/pre&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
It takes 30s to test 100 words. So to test british-english would take
8 hours.  New plan: find a list of words for emotions on the internet. &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://www.derose.net/steve/resources/emotionwords/ewordsRanked.txt&quot;&gt;like
  so&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~700 words, so under 5m to test them all. Doesn't work.&lt;/li&gt;


  &lt;li&gt;How about solving the captcha, verifying it, then sending 10
  verify requests for random words, then trying to verify the correct
  answer again? Fails.&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;How about trying a random word, then trying the correct answer?
  Fails.&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;How about trying the correct answer twice? Works both times.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ol&gt;

 &lt;p&gt;
Even though the key space is quite small, O(100)s of words, brute forcing
is hard because any false answer drops the session.  &lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;


This is more robust than I expected. A lot of the attacks I expected
to work don't work. There are fairly few questions, but the questions
don't matter. There are O(100s) of text answers, but its generating a new
image for each request, meaning that there isn't any point in solving the
images offline (or spending time trying to use their site as a oracle
for the images).  It reduces down to the normal image captcha problem -
OCRing images online. Its also probably vulnerable to dos attacks on
opening many sessions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-script: actually reading their docs shows that its based on &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.phpcaptcha.org/&quot;&gt;php captcha&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//san-pedro</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//san-pedro.html"/>
    <title>San Pedro de Atacama</title>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; Quick update, mostly to let my Mum know we haven't been kidnapped. We
are in San Pedro de Atacama in Chile. The Atacama is the driest desert on
Earth. We've been out for a walk, and its not as dry as I expected -
there are streams and life along the watercourses. Of course, where
there is no water, there is just dust.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The journey was spectacular - massive salt flats, colourful rocks,
and more wildlife, including flamingos. We're popping back to take a
closer look at the flamingos tomorrow. Laura is hoping to see the rare
James' flamingo, avocets and any other waders that might be hanging around above
4000 meters. The pass at the top of the Andes is 4170
meters - high enough to cause headaches, weird tingling in the fingers,
and a bit of nausea. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/dwvYRBARv6uI7u50VY21LZlmM7l98u8CAR2_nvvPmYo?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-kA9Y38NBQFE/UMimaSKQ6KI/AAAAAAAAIxw/DpjXtMpxCgs/s400/P1040888.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/VSX3XTwJNoIeUJoM9BiACZlmM7l98u8CAR2_nvvPmYo?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-2JPjwupYX2Y/UMinQ_Et_NI/AAAAAAAAIy0/InW3bxEBgBo/s400/P1040964.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/aoVa8dV7YEIoPDcf_tsZ7plmM7l98u8CAR2_nvvPmYo?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-wFJOUPjrKvQ/UMinQJ63dhI/AAAAAAAAIyw/19b5O3ycbYE/s400/P1040930.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/e2kAMLutbBmlncQTEEvy35lmM7l98u8CAR2_nvvPmYo?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-WO8l4yI1o20/UMilGdsX6vI/AAAAAAAAIxk/hzeBkxtlDQw/s400/P1050024.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt; We're been out stargazing, and the town is lovely. Not much more to
report. &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/RoadToSanPedroDeAtacama?authuser=0&amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCIH0-9K2xuq2tAE&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;The
  whole album&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//cloud-forest</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//cloud-forest.html"/>
    <title>Birding in the Cloud Forest</title>
    <updated>2012-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; On Friday, we rolled out of bed and attempted to get to El Ray
National park.  Sadly, the rain was not on our side. The road to El
Ray is a 47km dirt track with many river crossings, and our guide -
who was in a real 4x4 - didn't fancy doing it in the driving rain.
Instead we headed for his local birding spots, and on the way back
towards Salta he demonstrated the realness of his 4x4 (and the fact it
wasn't a chelsea tractor) by pulling another car out of a ditch on a
flooded road. The rescue was very Argentina - everyone stopped, and
half the local males got out, started running around in rain and the
deep mud helping, finding rope, tying it to the car and to our 4x4,
and in the end pulling the car and passengers to safety. The other
half of the population lent on their horns - we've even seen drivers
toot at the cops here (The garda would find a reason to arrest you
if you did that). Final twist to the rescue was our guide producing a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sLS3RGesIFQ&quot;&gt;Crocodile dundee
knife&lt;/a&gt; to cut the rope off the front of his car. (Final final twist -
Laura found a online review of a tour near Salta that described a mostly
silent guide leading his party deeper and deeper into the forest, slashing
at vegetation as he went. I'm pretty certain I've seen that movie).  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, he took us birding, both by the lake and into the cloud forest. He was
fantastic and we saw a lot. Photos I'm happy with:&lt;/p&gt;.

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Za1ID_GtNg_ACqkdYpHo-kiyP5ihtIc4N9_DVAIvlq0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uEzT7FjQpt8/UMO12wK9jSI/AAAAAAAAIpw/Pu1yY3_HfXQ/s400/P1000879.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/-x-tPKN933Bu_u9B7zUgEUiyP5ihtIc4N9_DVAIvlq0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-AimPzE2i3n0/UMOygCjg6nI/AAAAAAAAIns/uJFUtESa6DQ/s400/P1000843.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rdUJAmgoB2mx5dx1HUei60iyP5ihtIc4N9_DVAIvlq0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-aw5NKRzfmU0/UMOtYvMuf9I/AAAAAAAAIkA/JQSBJ37w_yg/s400/P1000739.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/5PL1fYfI7Tp_1Tps4-HBNkiyP5ihtIc4N9_DVAIvlq0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-bEcaRyB2iCw/UMUOTBAaRmI/AAAAAAAAIu0/fkNycWMstaA/s400/P1000730.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;293&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8bwSQB4UPGWTuvnKPCcoS0iyP5ihtIc4N9_DVAIvlq0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/--0VDxVTDGEI/UMUbTzVeRXI/AAAAAAAAIv0/aJrTbsZ3cqw/s400/P1000880.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;274&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/tXmERt7tzOlUsR7jOBk2eUiyP5ihtIc4N9_DVAIvlq0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-vKhYeMHn7mo/UMO1Pvc_UmI/AAAAAAAAIpU/ZGLiJc4Jsqk/s400/P1000865.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spot the hummingbird in the last frame :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/BirdsOfTheCloudForestAndALake?authuser=0&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;The whole album.&lt;/a&gt;  We got to spend a night at Selva Montana Ecolodge
which is a great place and has fresh milk - the first we've had since
leaving Ireland. If you're wondering - we went with Mario from &lt;a
    href=&quot;http://www.clarkexpediciones.com/&quot;&gt;clark expediciones&lt;/a&gt; -
    well worth it!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//cachi-roadtrip</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//cachi-roadtrip.html"/>
    <title>Road trip to Cachi</title>
    <updated>2012-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; We didn't do very much on Monday - we had hopes of going to the &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://www.maam.gob.ar/&quot;&gt;museum&lt;/a&gt;, but it
was closed. The museum would defy all attempts to visit it. We did do a
pile of planning and sorting stuff out, as well as tromping up the local
hill. On Tuesday, we jumped in a hire car and took off on a road trip.
&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;

We drove the southern tourist loop from Salta  - down to Cafayate, up
a smaller road to Cachi, then though Los Cardones national park back to
Salta. The lady in the tourist information office assured us we could do
this in two days, sadly, this was not the case.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The road down to Cafayate was kinda boring until we got into the
desert in Quebrada de Cafayate. Once again, weird and wonderful rock
formations drawn by the wind and water. It was a lovely fast drive,
although the Salta traffic is insane.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/YCYm7AsUEK66tIp4qCLu1nTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-HT3mSFVCs6A/UMOa9wNFF7I/AAAAAAAAIeI/3ep5HMP3S_k/s400/P1040626.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/aeN1JQ1v3i-rZdFXB8fRbXTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-dJhApP9KOyg/UMOLhX3M-TI/AAAAAAAAIZQ/TpP8Gfnltfk/s400/P1040635.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Cafayate is a lovely place. Its the second town in Argentina for
wine, and if you are looking for a place to drink wine, go there rather
than Mendoza. The local wine even comes in ice cream form! We wandered
around for a while, drank some of the local wine, ate empanadas while
drinking more wine from a jug, and peeked at the local museum - tons
of pottery recovered from local archaeological digs. The best find in
the local wine is torrontes - its a lovely white that people say is
hard to get outside Argentina and in our opinion beats Sauvignon blanc
hands down. We were a bit pushed for time, so we couldn't stay a day,
much as we wanted to.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/dP0cFKPfgwIFtVTWnDuG33TsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-BmL_och-koY/UMOMWH0XQ-I/AAAAAAAAIZk/cqAY_O3pOZU/s400/P1040649.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/-OU6ZRO3f2Pzb5D97itoXHTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-YuWekiWex9o/UMOhvsbBCBI/AAAAAAAAIfM/W7zU4MwYWf0/s400/P1000583.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The drive to Cachi was mostly on dirt roads. We set out zooming along
on tarmac, through vineyards, looking at wonderful mountains with the sun
blazing down. We overtook a local in his junker. One of the things that
got me when I moved to Ireland is that one sees more cars with dented
paneling etc than one does in the UK. Argentina lowers the standards
a lot more :-). There are plenty of cars from the 60s, 70s and 80s on
the road and some are about 50% rust on the outside, so who knows what
state the axles, suspension etc are in. We promptly hit the dirt road,
and crawled along at 30 kilometres a hour. The local promptly overtook
us, going much the same speed as he was going on tarmac. We laughed.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The scenery on the drive is Fantastic. Look at the pictures!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/wa3eph_Q0BIlW80Civ6coXTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-rIgz7z6TkW8/UMONW-oi9MI/AAAAAAAAIaE/alotQSJpRA8/s400/P1040694.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/vbUtmXOPgjDB68WU7CZbKHTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-q-gE7IxIoFk/UMOkV0dbwUI/AAAAAAAAIgM/J2xq30jrVeg/s400/P1000630.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

We saw parrots, woodpeckers, a small American Kestrel and a few Crested
Caracaras among other birds.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ujdVEkDTfBnfqSDY3Y7AGXTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-TU-C2Z-sWoM/UMOilbc4UQI/AAAAAAAAIfc/3c7NKjGLNaY/s400/P1000592.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/f2FQBL96EGb8NxyfpZHA4HTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-CibwZolN9-4/UMOifmXhgCI/AAAAAAAAIfU/LvSgqa0hiaY/s400/P1000604.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/71AMYpK7zMWKJvgJ6sDGCnTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-j-6gsnE4QeQ/UMOl2pHOuQI/AAAAAAAAIhE/6ryNiUUtH4k/s400/P1000677.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

We got a flat about 20 kilometers from Cachi. The car had been shaking
about so much we didn't hear it go, but a passerby tooted to let us
know. Two people who had never changed a tyre before (myself and Laura,
if there is any confusion) jumped out, jacked the car up, and promptly
failed to loosen the nuts. No amount of stomping, standing, and brute
force would move the nuts. In the meantime, the car was heating up -
by the end I couldn't hold my camera and the steering wheel was being
held with fingertips. We asked a local for help in poor Spanish  - he
did the same stomping routine. He asked a friend, who had a extender for
the wrench. The extra metre of leverage did the trick. Science! The nuts
had probably expanded in the heat.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Since we were now without a spare tyre, had hundreds of kilometers on
dirt roads to go, and it was getting late, we stopped in Cachi. Phoned
up Hertz, who said they would deliver a spare in a hour or two. The guy
who was assigned to deliver the new spare looked at his map and decided
not to bother, and also not to tell anyone. Grr.  We spent the night in
a lovely hotel - El Cortijo Hotel Boutique. The thing about staying
in hostels is that when we stay in a hotel, we wander about going &quot;this
is so nice! Feel the sheets! And air con!&quot;. The view was also lovely.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt; &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/G8vflnt1De4fn-Z0DbxMAHTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-oSpvgUHLRV8/UMOPVXGB0vI/AAAAAAAAIbY/rF11kP7RKrE/s400/P1040745.JPG&quot;
  height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p&gt;

In the morning, we found the local tyre dealership (a massive operation -
something tells me the owner doesn't want the road paved), got a new tyre,
and set off.  The road down to Salta is a fun drive. Through Los
Cardones national park, the road is as straight as the eye could see,
and lined with warnings about speed being enforced. I figure that once or
twice a year the cops go and ticket everyone for racing on the road. The
park is stuffed full of cactus. A legend tells of a priest who fled
over the plateau at night - thinking the cacti were Indians chasing him.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/7Nq33oA8en4KjTwraEuYFHTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-btxG52VNoIw/UMORKhHyP6I/AAAAAAAAIcQ/SbKiS-7nyEk/s400/P1040762.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8hyXSl_X4hBAqJJYm_qDxXTsYTndMeBasiFsbquMPUY?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/--QiHHYZwfaA/UMOQ3x0EuII/AAAAAAAAIcE/onaBGcVtFCc/s400/P1040760.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

The lack of turns in the park is made up for by the road down from it. The
Satellite photo fails to show that it loses about 2000 metres in height - and
its unpaved. The photo of the edge is a bit too scary.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot;
  marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;
  src=&quot;https://maps.google.com/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=-25.175583,-65.844154&amp;amp;spn=0.043732,0.084543&amp;amp;t=k&amp;amp;z=14&amp;amp;output=embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br
/&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;https://maps.google.com/?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=-25.175583,-65.844154&amp;amp;spn=0.043732,0.084543&amp;amp;t=k&amp;amp;z=14&amp;amp;source=embed&quot;
    style=&quot;color:#0000FF;text-align:left&quot;&gt;View Larger Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

We just about managed to navigate around Salta and get the car back
in time.  In short, if you're planning on going - go to Cafayate for
wine, take a few days to drive there and back (not two), and take a
wrench extender!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Other advice for fellow travelers is to be prepared for the money
situation here. In short it is crazy. Lots of small towns have no ATM
or ATMs which run out of money.  That's OK, it's South America and
we've managed to plan and carefully budget our way around it. What
is more frustrating is that even in large towns many places including
accommodation (decent hotels included) and restaurants will not take
card payments. This means that if you are travelling to an area with no
ATM you need to start extracting the money days in advance due to the
limit of cash that you can take out in one day. It also means that if you
are staying for a few nights in one accommodation you need to start the
withdrawal process days ahead in order to be able to pay at check-out. The
other approach is to come with money in several current accounts.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/CafayateAndCachiRoadTrip?authuser=0&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;All the photos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//desert</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//desert.html"/>
    <title>The Desert</title>
    <updated>2012-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We are in Salta, after many hours on buses. &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/ValleFertilToSalta?authuser=0&amp;feat=directlink&quot;&gt;album
  link&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
We can tell you are not from around here, you are so white. -- some gent to
Laura.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;vital stats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location:  Salta, Argentina. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;beard state: I found a razor. I'm happy about this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;steak tally: 7 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; We left Mendoza on the bus to San Juan. We found ourselves with a
hour and a half layover there, almost all of it went into talking to bus
companies about tickets. Transactions that would be trivial back home are
nightmares of spanglish and pointing here. We then headed out into
the desert - miles and miles of desert - to San Agustin de Valle Fertil
(which everyone calls Valle Fertil). The bus ride was pretty comfortable,
apart from whenever we crossed a dried  up watercourse. Rather than
bridging the drop, or filling in the drop, the road just dropped down
and up again. The bus driver, being used to this sort of thing, thought
slowing down was weak.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name comes from the valley being more fertile than the
desert, not because its more fertile than, say, Ireland. Its a really
nice place and we recommend it. The hostel reviews on tripadvisor were
scary, so we checked into a hotel. Turns out this was a wise move as the
local campsite also appears to be a scrapyard, and shortly after we got
to the hotel, it started to hail massive stones. This would have made getting
the tent up something of a challenge.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--

Be nice to have a photo here
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The reason people come to Valle Fertil is that its the closest place to
two parks in the desert, &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talampaya_National_Park&quot;&gt;Talampaya
  National Park&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ischigualasto&quot;&gt;Ischigualasto
  Provincial Park&lt;/a&gt;. These are still well over a hundred
kilometers from Valle Fertil. Both parks are colossal, but both let visitors
into a small area of the park by tour only.  Both are famous fossil grounds,
and one has rare and enigmatic pteroglyphs. Both have all extremes of
weather (burning hot with no shade in the day, freezing at night, high
winds, and sometimes snow lying on the cacti). I think they don't want
people stealing stuff or being sunburnt to death.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We went on the tour of both, which is a 11 hour day. We got a local driver to do
the driving. I would suggest that route for other folks interested in visiting -
rather than taking two trips over two days. We think the three days of
travelling there and back were well worth it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Talampaya had a tour of the canyon system, miles of desert,
red rock shaped by wind and water, and traces of the civilisation that
lived there 6000 years ago.  The pteroglyphs are tiny and hard to see -
its incredible that people found them again. The canyons have a smear of
green where the river has shrunk too, but there are traces of water
a few feet up the canyons walls. Fear the flash flood.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;

  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/yX4VlX6U3RLLxCaZtgQf09tzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-i9htf0JenqI/ULqcPRRA3_I/AAAAAAAAHpg/0AF9wadIx2s/s400/P1040286.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    hrefe&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/adZpEvRL4K1ujkxwXGMxVttzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-bYg2Q-0ooC8/ULqdNmTHe8I/AAAAAAAAHqM/QYVswCw2CD0/s400/P1040300.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The view out over the desert looks like nothing else I have seen. The rock
formations are fantastic. I'm hoping the photos do them justice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/XfZ8k8s0D7lxhKpp2QLaMttzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-6c2g43OrtlU/ULqeJzS-ZzI/AAAAAAAAHqk/g2wqZmBvJZM/s400/P1040346.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Qp4aj6Rz7wG4AyiItLnl0ttzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-SwzjJto0A58/ULqdLJccClI/AAAAAAAAHp8/DynZSPJvOcw/s400/P1040303.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Pdi1lXLGPOooXFPxrJtcY9tzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-OlQMr-ShJ-4/ULqfCyj8rJI/AAAAAAAAHq0/FRy47OgypRU/s400/P1040364.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


We whizzed off to Parque Provincial Ischigualasto. The landscape here is
like another planet.  My first impressions were of a dry dusty landscape
and a wind that threatened to blow the doors off the car. The on-site
museum protects the fossils from the wind and the water.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The tour is conducted from your car - in our case the ranger rode in the
front seat - and it was excellent. This would not be a place to bring
your own car, unless you hate the paintwork. The landscape lives up to
the name Valle de la Luna - valley of the moon. A barren, lifeless,
dusty gray landscape, marked only by the ravages of the wind and the
occasional rainstorms. The ranger said this was the closest to the moon
surface we could go to without leaving Earth.  We saw fossils
in the rock, more wildlife, and spectacular rock formations. Having the
ranger explain the local bird life was great. Hopefully we'll stick up
some of the photos from Laura's camera.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/BkNeF1_oQ6KQh_tNVWEQK9tzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-YnHVX42VCw8/ULqhBpAUbFI/AAAAAAAAHsA/4qgTBnigaQ8/s400/P1040473.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Gqa4JQq7wxt62nQb7vh6i9tzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Uc2fvAT5azU/ULqh_xyyP3I/AAAAAAAAHsY/UiclZDTDIj8/s400/P1040500.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rkeOlgzCj7Qb2_-CSy4bittzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-P3RijiilDG8/ULqi7W16GOI/AAAAAAAAHso/Q1Y4XhZFRYw/s400/P1040502.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We spent the morning afterwards wandering around the town - the local
museum was either closed or being used to store loud, violent dogs -
and up by the lake we saw birds and an iguana.  This is the first time
we have seen one in the wild!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The bus back to San Juan was much the same, though it was carrying a
couple of cops. As far as I can see, the police in Argentina are either
slackers of the highest order, or never bother to take their uniforms
and guns off. One does see them cuddling their girlfriends while in
uniform. We still have not been shaken down.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

San Juan is off the backpacking trail, so us with our crazy backpacks was the
talk of the town. Much discussion of the size of Ireland compared to Argentina,
the greenness of Ireland, if we were German, and my or my mum's view of Scottish
independence.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had many hours between buses in San Juan, so we went out for dinner. The
steakhouse not merely had a window into the kitchen (watch the flames! Watch the
chef hacking giant lumps of meat then tossing them onto his barbecue), it served
the largest steak I have ever seen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/0o6xFrctAzpPEuRkLF9z09tzLUQvM8bkyDzY5OCS7H8?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-0yDvda7mVU0/ULqk3PTLuJI/AAAAAAAAHtw/bQx7S4zqWYE/s400/P1040614.JPG&quot;
    height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Of course, by the time we had eaten, we were massively short on time,
leading to a fast taxi ride and a sprint up the bus station steps. The
bus was a bit late, saving our bacon. This was a 16 hour overnight bus
trip, and we had been worrying about it. Turns out that the bus ride was
pretty nice - more comfortable than anything up to business class. Seats
recline, wine and dinner at your seats (wine great, dinner terrible),
tons of leg room. This put British public transport (and every airline
I've flown with) to shame.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Salta is very nice, though we haven't seen much of it so far.
Having spent three and a half days on buses in the last week, we want
to be based in Salta for a while. The plan is to head back into Chile
for the new moon.  &lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//mendoza</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//mendoza.html"/>
    <title>Through the Andes to Mendoza</title>
    <updated>2012-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
  We are in Mendoza, Argentina. This place claims to be the wine capital of the
  world.
  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;vital stats&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Location:  Mendoza, Argentina. &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;beard state: I can not wait to find a razor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ping time to nuttall.im: 273ms. &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;ping time to google.com: 58ms .&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;steak tally: 3 (and a pile of BBQ). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt; We took the bus here. Its quite  a &lt;a
    href=&quot;http://maps.google.com/?ll=-32.85385,-70.126505&amp;spn=0.040882,0.084543&amp;t=h&amp;z=14&quot;&gt;ride&lt;/a&gt;.
    The border crossing was mental, we
  were there for 2 hours. Apparently that is standard and can be
  longer. The scenery was fantastic but it is all very dry. We arrived
  in Mendoza to find that the hostel was having an &lt;i&gt;asado&lt;/i&gt; - an Argentine
  barbecue. After all day on the bus this went down a storm. There was
  great wine out of unmarked bottles
  and we met some good folks from
  various countries. The meat is as tasty as people say, juicier and
  with more flavour than anything we've had before.  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Notes for folks interested in the same journey - you get the bus from
  Universidad de Santiago, its worth booking in advance (we hung around the bus station for
  hours until the bus went),and Chilean bus rides are both cheap and
  comfortable.
  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;
  Today we went to Maipu to cycle around vineyards on a tandem. It was good but
  hard work figuring out where to go and how to pay. There's a major shortage of
  coins in Argentina. Our bus card ran out of money and there was nowhere to put
  credit on it but fortunately the driver let us travel back to Mendoza for
  free. The good news was we ate excellent food and drank wine before fighting
  the bus.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a
      href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/OGgDEw99n4lF_yX7vNgco9MTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
      src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-5tyhY5j6hXY/ULVxc0rqQfI/AAAAAAAAHlo/J5px2iMwfG8/s400/P1040155.JPG&quot;
      height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;

  Simple things have become difficult. There is no obvious system when it comes
  to crossing the road so it is always dicey. There are giant holes in the
  pavement that threaten to suck you into a subterranean underworld. There are
  some fancy new cars but most of them are ancient and are hanging apart and
  totally battered. When we were on the bus we saw a guy riding in the back of a
  pick up truck on a fast road when there was a perfectly good passenger seat.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
Communicating is difficult but we are picking up more words bit by bit.
Fortunately the people here are very patient and helpful. The pronounciation in
both Chile and Argentina is quite different which means that sometimes we are
not understood when we speak what we were taught. It is amazing how many people
have un &lt;i&gt;poco de ingles&lt;/i&gt; though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is roasting hot. We are leaving here tomorrow and heading on to San Agustin
de Valle Fertil to see some national parks. Yet another day on the buses.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//santiago-again</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//santiago-again.html"/>
    <title>Santiago</title>
    <updated>2012-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We are back in Santiago, where the internet flows freely and there is an
English-speaking church full of welcoming people. We are having a rest day, and
will be on the bus tomorrow to go to Mendoza in Argentina. The great thing about
having working internet is we can upload some photos, links below.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/EasterIsland02&quot;&gt;Easter
    Island&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/Santiago&quot;&gt;Santiago&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/LauraSEasterIsland&quot;&gt;More
    of Easter Island&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/GettingOutOfTheDoor&quot;&gt;Getting
    out of the Door&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The flight out of Easter Island was somewhat amusing. We hauled down the tent,
then hauled our stuff to the airport (which looked like airports the world over,
with the exception of a pile of island-este artwork). When we checked in - a
process of signing many many releases for our baggage, they explained the flight
was delayed for four hours. This explanation was communicated by giving us a
pile of lunch vouchers. It turns out that the rules of the air (namely, feed
people when delayed) apply even if one is on a small volocano in the south
pacific. Other rules that seem to apply include drinking all water before
getting on plane. Rules that get ignored include removing all metal from pockets
before going though the detector.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the airport is a runway and a large shed, we were whisked off to a place
in town for lunch at the expense of LAN. Said place had not had their delivery
of food for the day. The sole thing they offered was garlic prawns. Pause. We
could not imagine why they were on the menu to begin with. We clearly saw why
they were the only things that the diners last night had not eaten. We worried
about being on a plane for many hours with large numbers of people who had all
eaten garlic prawns. We did not worry about vampires. We did worry about food
poisoning. The waitress saw our faces and said they also had some smoked salmon.
Saved!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The last couple days on the island were fun. We took a boat out around the sea
stack Motu Kau Kau and another two &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motu_Nui&quot;&gt;islands&lt;/a&gt;. We saw Masked Boobys
and Great Frigatebirds. It was wonderful but  many other species of seabirds
once nested on the islands so it was also a reminder of the consequences of
unsustainable exploitation and overgrazing among other ecological issues.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/dUANekw-JHGqe5IXYTm-L9MTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-HBVFwjWyCn8/ULJntKjmuqI/AAAAAAAAHNE/IWlD1_695Fg/s400/P1030887.JPG&quot;
  height=&quot;270&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/J-Rkk2yFCi_Nc316voU6PdMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/--y1zpvF-1gM/ULJnuN0q8JI/AAAAAAAAHNQ/dcs-fbmNaeo/s400/P1030782.JPG&quot;
  height=&quot;254&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We tromped up &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rano_Kau&quot;&gt;Rano Kau&lt;/a&gt;, an
old volcano with the ceremonial village &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orongo&quot;&gt;Orongo&lt;/a&gt; on the top. The view
into the crater is like looking at another landscape altogether. The village
consists of many restored stone buildings, which reminded me of &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skara_Brae&quot;&gt;Skara Brae&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/m1VnAg5u-67_jjdWLmd9TtMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Xd9e1ksSKds/ULJn1_wWaDI/AAAAAAAAHPY/rto2JThXPKM/s400/P1030956.JPG&quot;
  /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/razwMl95fP61GPdGibFhrdMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
  src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4L0YHPdvjeU/ULJn7MpmF8I/AAAAAAAAHN4/k60diqjGtEg/s400/P1030975.JPG&quot;
  /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the last night we found ourselves in a small restaurant which a couple at the
campsite suggested. Turns out this place had a giant barbeque. We found
ourselves stuffed with only a few bites... on average we're eating about two
meals a day, partly due to the heat, partly due to lack of need for more. The
way we wash our clothes has also changed:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;photo&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/VmIyZizV5hl2dlp3ZCcqBtMTjNZETYmyPJy0liipFm0?feat=embedwebsite&quot;&gt;&lt;img
    src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-V6ut8k5hw6w/ULKMhmIZCTI/AAAAAAAAHd8/U696vvqCbuU/s400/P1000395.JPG&quot;
    /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//easter-island</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//easter-island.html"/>
    <title>Easter Island</title>
    <updated>2012-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We are on Easter Island. It is a magical place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;vital stats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;


  &lt;li&gt;Location: Easter Island, about 2000 miles from the chilean coast, about
    8000 miles from the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;beard state: bristly and annoying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ping time to nuttall.im: 2212ms. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ping time to google.com: 1306ms (and 15% packet loss).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;steak tally: 3 Laura thinks we should keep a tally. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We flew in on Monday, watched a massive downpour
from the airport concourse, and  got a ride to the campsite. The fact that the
ride was in the load-bed of a pickup truck did suggest that this was a different
place.
We pitched the tent, and went for a look around. There are palm, coconut and
banana trees all over the place. No one wears seatbelts.
The Chilean naval base looks like a beach hut. We have taken hundreds of photos,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/22112012&quot;&gt;A crude
  sneak preview.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The statues are massive and eerie. We spent some time staring at them. There are
no signs as to why they are there or how they were made.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Pete They must have been raised by aliens. Wait, I probably said that
  yesterday. &lt;br /&gt;
  Laura: Yesterday you just pointed and said aliens! aliens!
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tuesday we went horse riding up to the top of the Island. This was massively
painful, and was probably a mistake. We are plotting making a parody of I´m on a
horse.
Afterwards we staggered around the museum
(very much like Newgrange - they have no idea why the statues are there) and
then wandered into town to drink picso sours until we stopped hurting. The local
beer is wonderful too.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday we rented a car (a fake 4x4 - it looked the part but didn´t have four
wheel drive) and zoomed around the sites. The sites are wonderful - hundreds of
statues just standing there.
We drove around to the island´s beach, which was paradise. White sand, lovely
clear water, coconut trees.
We watched the fishes swim past - a sight I have never seen in Britain or Ireland.
There were flat fish and schools of smaller fish and the occasional large fish
of different sorts.
The beach had a excellent warning sign: danger, falling coconuts. It was just
spectactular.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Notes from Laura:
Car hire here is very simple, you ask for a car and you get the keys, no
questions asked about a licence and no insurance. The locals ride around in the
back of trucks and whole families
ride around on a single motorbike without helmets. The Daihatsu chugged along
and the engine sounded knackered. As soon as we got off the tarmac road and on
to the dirt tracks we knew why
all the controls felt so loose and shaky.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The bird diversity here is low although there are islands offshore which are
important for seabirds. The highlight so far has been Red-tailed tropicbirds.
Common diuca finchs are everywhere
but they are non native. One bird of prey species is also everywhere
and is probably the Chimango Caracara can´t be sure yet. Now back to Pete...
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We´re met some interesting people here. Main source of giggling was an american
family on the horse riding trip.
The adult son was on his gap year in Buenos Aires, and the parents had flown
down to vist him and tour the sites.
Half way around the riding, Mum started nagging son about the fact he was not
wearing sun cream on the back of his neck. &quot;But mum, I do not want toooo&quot;.
We also watched a guy run around the statues at Rano Raraku. He also did
handstands in front of them. He was quietly mocked by a pair of german women
walking ahead of us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I sense the nerds might be interested in the internet connection. I suspect a
sat connection. It has about 10kbs of bandwidth.
I also think the router here is doing dialup to a number in mainland Chile,
since its the second hop of the traceroute that has the crazy latency.
ssh is pretty show but not terrible. web browsing is painful. The Picasa
uploader for photos is useless. I think there are a few sites out there thinking
we are doing a slowaris attack.
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//valpanasio</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//valpanasio.html"/>
    <title>Valparaiso</title>
    <updated>2012-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; Yesterday we went to Valparaiso, which is home to the planet's
strategic reserve of Napoleonic tat. Its a lovely port on the coast near
Santiago. It was a happening place until an earthquake and the opening of
the Panama Canal pretty much wiped it out. Sir Francis Drake torched the
place, so they are always happy when more brits show up. (just kidding).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; In the good old days, ships bound for California had to sail around
Cape Horn in the very south of Chile, then past tons of Patagonian  fjords
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slartibartfast&quot;&gt;Slartibartfast&lt;/a&gt;
would be proud), until getting to Valparaiso, the first real port. The opening
off the canal cut off the need to go around Cape Horn. It also cut off
Valparaiso's source of income. The main things of note in the town now
are the Naval College and port. We wandered around Naval Muesum, which
hangs off the College.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More history: The Royal Navy began a massive demobilisation as Napoleon
was shipped off to Elba. At the same time, the South American republics were
fighting for independence from Spain. The Chilean founding fathers (one of whom has a
massively confused ancestry and the surname O'Higgins, making many street names
sound familar) suggested to out-of-work Royal Navy officers that they might like
a job. The prize catch of this was &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cochrane,_10th_Earl_of_Dundonald&quot;&gt;Thomas
  Cochrane&lt;/a&gt;, who is a big deal in the history of the Chilean Navy. Approx one
and a half Nelson's worth of a deal. The museum goes into this in some detail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The main problem the museum has is that Chile hasn't actually been at war with
anyone for over 100 years. The Coup is politely brushed over, though there is a
room about a admiral who ended up in charge, with no discussion of how he became
president.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The rest of the town is lovely - full of narrow winding streets, street murals,
funicular railways, and a wonderful view. Go for a wander if you're ever there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon we wandered up &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Crist%C3%B3bal_Hill&quot;&gt;San Cristobal
  Hill&lt;/a&gt;. The view from the top over Santiago is immense. The city sprawls
for miles.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have actually managed to put up photos from &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/Valparaiso&quot;&gt;Valparaiso.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//wandering</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//wandering.html"/>
    <title>Wandering around Santiago</title>
    <updated>2012-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We have been in Santiago for about two days now. In real terms, this is the end
of our stay. We had assumed we would conk out due to jetlag, but that has not
really happened. I think this is due to the time difference being pretty small
- only three hours - and due to us being tired enough to sleep on the flight.
We are staying at a lovely hostel in Barrio Brasil. Its a old building, full
of wood panelling. We do not know what it was before it was a hostel - the guy on
the desk thinks it was a government building.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

The Hostel is in a area full of car parts shops. Every single business seems
to be a car parts shop. No idea why. No one we have asked knows why. In the
middle of the neighbourhood is a monkey puzzle tree. All the buildings are old
and dusty and coming apart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

On the first day, we took the metro out to Las Condes - a modern neighbourhood
that reminded me of Vancouver. Its has the same high rise glass buildings and
looming mountains. Unlike Canada the mountains are brown - the same colour as
the hills over the bay from San Francisco, but much closer and much bigger.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

One of the things I like here is that eating and drinking often takes place
outside, on the street. The climate supports that. Every now and again, some
crazy guy suggests that Edinburgh could have the same cafe culture. Then it
starts raining and people make fun of him.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;


On the first night we ate in a great restaurant and had our first pisco sours, a
favourite drink here. They are made from distilled grapes and are very
refreshing. Calf testicles were on the menu but we avoided them and had raw wild
boar instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

The second day we wandered out of the neighbourhood around the hostel and
into la centro. We toured the old buildings of Santiago. The national
museum is a very old building just off the central square, is pretty
much incomprehensible without a good grasp of spanish. It also cuts
right on a coup in 1973, which was a bit creepy. We then wandered over
to the presidential palace and the statue of Allende.  The main thing
thats different about here is that all the old buildings, offices of
government etc are overshadowed by lots of massive grey tower blocks.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

We wandered up Cerro Santa Lucia - a hill near the center of town. Looked out
over miles of tower blocks and smog. We wandered through the rush hour traffic -
which is completely insane by the way, I feel like I am taking an advanced course in
jay-walking - into Barro Bellavista. This neighbourhood reminded me of Fremont
in Seattle, though without the &quot;set your watch back five minutes&quot; sign.  We
shunned climbing up a hill to see the papal statue.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ate curry for dinner. Its not that, uh, exotic, but we freaked out at the
idea that we might not eat curry for three months. Was good. So far, a good time
being had by all. Had hoped to get some photos on the web, but that has not
happened yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//google-auth</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//google-auth.html"/>
    <title>Google Authenticator</title>
    <updated>2012-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Warning&lt;/b&gt; More nerd content. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself typing this (and the post before it) over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html&quot;&gt;Putty&lt;/a&gt; (Note for the more twitchy - Strong encryption is legal in England (where is computer is) and Chile and Argentina. The list of countries that outlaw strong encryption is pretty similar to the list of countries with records of making citizens vanish.) Putty does not understand ssh keys in whatever format openssh uses. I dare not dig deeper. Having a system where I download a ssh key onto a untrusted machine is not wise. Having a system where I enter a password into a untrusted machine also is not wise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deal with this, I set up &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/google-authenticator/wiki/PamModuleInstructions&quot;&gt;Google
  authenticator&lt;/a&gt; for pam. This works pretty well so far - on a trusted
machine, I can continue to use ssh keys, and on a untrusted machine, I can use
the same one time system as I use for email etc. I also have rescue codes in my
pocket incase I lose my phone.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//santiago</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//santiago.html"/>
    <title>Santiago</title>
    <updated>2012-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt; We've made it to Santiago! Long trip, lots of packing. Looking
forward to decompressing a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Vital stats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location: Santiago, Chile.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beard state: soft sandpaper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ping time to google.com: 42ms (200.10.266.231)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ping time to nuttall.im: 290ms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

When I was a kid I played &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spycat&quot;&gt;Spycat&lt;/a&gt; which
depicts a guy trying to get his stuff together and leave London. Thats
roughly what the last few days have been like, without the cctv and
the eighties parody. After two days of solid packing and little sleep,
we made it to the airport with all our stuff - thanks to Mark our pastor
for giving us a lift :-)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We flew into Madrid airport. The plane was only about a third full
- probably should have been a warning sign - and the pilot didn't think
much of this new-fangled concept of keeping his plane going in a straight
line on takeoff. The airport was massive and completely empty. It was like
wandering around in a ghost town. The size and quiet brought to mind a
concrete cathedral. It reminded me of the new terminal at Dublin before
it got airlines, or the cinema in eastpoint. Why do countries always
decide to upgrade their capital airport just before the money runs out?

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; We had a many hour wait for the next flight, so we popped
into Madrid on the metro. The metro was completely packed. Theory one:
Madrid is some sort of prison camp for obnoxious people from all over
Europe. They get carted off, taught spanish, and told to live there until
they get manners. The only reason we haven't heard about this is the
eurozone - if Britain would just join or Ireland would just stop losing
money, we too could ship our folks off to Madrid. I also suspect the
Spanish are dreading the arrival of Cameron. Theory two was that it was
rush hour, which has the advantage of being simple and is probably true.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
As I said, we've been working on speaking Spanish. Fears became flesh when
we heard the first announcement in Spanish on the plane. We're probably
doomed. Getting dinner in Madrid did nothing to reassure us. Leaving
the restaurant, we promptly found ourselves close to a demonstration,
along with many riot police. And when we got back to the airport, it was
announced that Spain was having a general strike. This possibly explains
the quiet airport.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

I read through &quot;In Patagonia&quot; and &quot;The old Patagonian express&quot; on the
flight; good reads. We'll probably get rid of the books soonish to save on
weight. Paul Theroux makes fun of travel books that talk about arriving in
places by plane &quot;the toy town appearance of a city in the Andes&quot; but for
us it wasn't like that. We got on the plane, rejected the food and fell
asleep. At some point - possibly after coffee - we flipped up the window
blinds and the Andes were right there. Quite a sight. (Note from Laura:
this is a classic case of Pete's reserve - it was an outstanding view).
&lt;/p&gt;

 &lt;p&gt; We've survived Chilean customs (quick panic about the pepper
pot we were carrying), pushed past the taxi drivers and got into town
by bus. First impressions are its somewhat like California. Its hot and
dusty, roads are big. They seem to be building concrete tower blocks
here - possibly due to the earthquake. Seems crazy to me to build high
and heavy on top of a fault line, but what do I know. Laura thinks the
place is crumbly. No idea what she means. I fear her apple crumble.
The hostel is nice, and has good internet. Woo.


&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//packing</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//packing.html"/>
    <title>packing</title>
    <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I watched &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_Exit_to_Springfield&quot;&gt;Last exit to
  Springfield&lt;/a&gt; twice. This must be what being unemployed is like. Soon I will
vote tory. In other news, I rang my british bank and asked them not to block my card.
They told me the blocking was done by an automatic system, it was impossible to
override said system, and it was for my protection. The back of my head went
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oOjXyarN3-Y&amp;feature=related&quot;&gt;duh duh dun-duh duh&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've been packing like crazy. Turns out that we have both way more and way less
stuff than we thought. The good news that stuff packs really well into our
storage space. The bad news is we have way too much stuff. Seems like we've been
packing for weeks and weeks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaguely amusing side story here - Laura has labelled the three euro boxes sold by
the storage place as a complete rip off, a scam more blatant than my folder full
of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigerian_scam&quot;&gt;419 mail.&lt;/a&gt; So we've
popped around to the local off licenses and picked up tons of old booze boxes. A
good chunk of them are for &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosecco&quot;&gt;Prosecco&lt;/a&gt;.
Who are our neighours? What are they celebrating? How do we get invites? The world is full
of questions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its not all cardboard and tape. Some recent photos from around the area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/99ViewsOfDublinBay&quot;&gt;two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/LastDaysOfDublin2012&quot;&gt; Last weekend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799/SunsetOverTheBay&quot;&gt;Somewhat older sunsets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The schedule is simple - tomorrow, put everything in storage, and wednesday,
get on plane ;-).&lt;/p




</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//updates</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//updates.html"/>
    <title>updates</title>
    <updated>2012-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;

I have one day of work left. My boss points out that I'm not being
fired, and I even get to keep my badge. And my
gun&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; id=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Sarah, our admin, can't wait to have another
free desk. She hasn't actually said &quot;when do you go? I need the space&quot;,
but she's thinking it hard. The other work related content is

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Laura: While you don't work for the daily mail, you do work for google,
which lets people find daily mail articles on cancer, so you're pretty much
internet Hitler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Laura's been making us learn Spanish. The idea is that we'll not
be one of those annoying people who expect the whole world to speak
English. Instead we'll be saying No lo entiendo a lot. The guide book
claims that Chile is one of the places where the locals are really glad
the visitors attempt to speak the language. Sounds like a lie. Reminds
me of the Norway guidebook that claimed that speed limits were carefully
followed and ruthlessly enforced.  At the point in which the tenth BMW
doing 150&amp;#37; of the limit blew past us, we saw the error of our
ways. Or the walking in Ireland book which directed us into not one but
two bogs. Getting to the top of one hill in the driving rain and miles
of bog, then seeing the dry trail up the other side wasn't a big enough
hint. A month or so later, still following the book, we found ourselves
sliding down a very boggy, very steep hillside. You might wonder how
one can have a non-flat bog. This is article seven of my mysteries of
Ireland questions, after such greats as pondering the celtic tiger,
the catholic church, and people still living in Limerick. Anyway,
ranting over. We will see how the Spanish works out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

I wandered along and got some Chilean and Argentine money earlier in the
evening. It came from the currency exchange place near Trinty college, which was
the only place in all of Dublin to have south american money. Said place gives
the faint air that its predecessor was target of a 4am ram raid. Or possibly a
ned with a shotgun. Its hard to tell.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Chilean money reminds me of the collapse of the Wilmar republic. Its
not that Chile is going into any sort of depression, its just that the
numbers are so big. Argentine money, on the other hand, is shaky enough
that places often just want to be paid in dollars. Sad.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've started packing. This is not going well.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;sup id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;1. Just kidding.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot; title=&quot;Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//trains</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//trains.html"/>
    <title>trains</title>
    <updated>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;Are the train tracks still broken?&quot;&lt;/i&gt; -- the internet&lt;/p&gt;


</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//flying</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//flying.html"/>
    <title>flying</title>
    <updated>2012-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
We've been looking at flying around. Laura has been worrying about the standards
of planes. Actual conversation this morning:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Pete: This plane looks completely normal.&lt;br /&gt;
Laura: Pete! Its like a hobby plane! &lt;br /&gt;
Pete:  Hey! Its got windows n stuff. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//nerdy-stuff</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//nerdy-stuff.html"/>
    <title>nerdy notes</title>
    <updated>2012-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
I'm a nerd. Here's some nerdy notes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

Cameras: I'm planning to take my point and shoot. its maybe
a year old. Its grand. Now the bad news is that I can take
a lot of photos - over 100 a day. So amazon sent us 10 8g sd
cards. Betcha we still run out. Betcha that I look at the idea
of only 80g of storage and laugh. I've also bought space on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://picasaweb.google.com/102479403334301156799&quot;&gt;Picasa&lt;/a&gt;
which was dead cheap. The hope there is that we'll be able to get the
originals back through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/takeout&quot;&gt;takeout&lt;/a&gt;
later. Facebook is much more of a pain in this respect. We've also got
some blank cds, which we'll try and back stuff up onto. The fear here
is both losing or damaging a SD card, and also theft.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My Camera can upload photos direct to the internet. Making this functionallity
work has been a pain in the backside. It also seems to drain the battery. We'll
see if it works out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

We'll probably want to get into email and facebook while
we're out there. We'll probably do it from internet
cafes with interesting collections of malware. So &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.mattcutts.com/blog/google-two-step-authentication/&quot;&gt;2
factor&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/note.php?note_id=10150172618258920&quot;&gt;SMS
auth&lt;/a&gt;. SMS auth is a bit more of a pain as we don't really know phone
numbers out there - experience and common sense argues for buying a new
sim card. I've also picked up a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yubico.com/yubikey&quot;&gt;yubikey&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://lastpass.com/&quot;&gt;lastpass&lt;/a&gt;. We'll probably still have
problems.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;

I'm taking an android phone, and to reduce the impact of it being lost or
stolen I've set up the android / google apps corp system for registering
phones &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/apps/mydevices&quot;&gt;the control
panel&lt;/a&gt;. It lets you ring phones, wipe phones remotely and tells you where
they are. Its a google apps for your domain feature that actually costs
money, but its pretty cheap. And it means I never lose my phone again. I also set
up the normal security settings - encrypting the phone and so on. We'll see.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This site is hosted on a little virtual machine sitting in London. To get into
it I depend on ssh keys. I've stuck those keys on my phone and can connect with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.google.com/p/connectbot/&quot;&gt;connectbot&lt;/a&gt;, but using a unix
text editor with a phone's keyboard may drive me insane. We'll see how much
blogging we do ;-). I have thought about putting &lt;a
  href=&quot;http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/&quot;&gt;putty&lt;/a&gt; and the
keys on a USB stick and plugging it into internet cafes - we'll see.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also have a kindle. I like the kindle as its dead light and has a ton of books
on it. Laura points out the kindle will probably be nicked. We'll see. At least
I bought a waterproof bag for it at some earlier point.
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//eating-up</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//eating-up.html"/>
    <title>eating up</title>
    <updated>2012-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Laura pointed out to me last night that we have been eating up bits of food (so
we don't have to throw it away when we go) since we got back from &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/photos/102479403334301156799/albums/5806918868281229841&quot;&gt;Salisbury&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/photos/102479403334301156799/albums/5806928066457692993&quot;&gt;Bruges&lt;/a&gt;.
Thats something like five weeks of eating. Worrying. However, we have made ribs
twice. Recipe is tasty and easy:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 spring onions, white part only, finely sliced&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 garlic cloves, crushed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon wholegrain mustard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon chilli paste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons hoisin sauce.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons mango chutney.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&amp;frac12; sea salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&amp;frac14; black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;125ml Coopers pale ale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 racks of american style ribs (600-700g)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Its really easy to make. Combine everything but the ribs together in a bowl -
this part smells pretty bad. Cut up the ribs into eatable sizes and stick
them in a deep tray. Pour the marinade over the ribs and leave them. The book says
for a hour or two, but we normally leave them for a day. Stick them in the oven
at a low heat for a hour or so, then grill them. Avoid comments from Laura about
the lack of salad, veg, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Swiped from the cooking with beer book my parents got us. Its a tasty tasty
book.
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//first-post</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//first-post.html"/>
    <title>First!</title>
    <updated>2012-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're off to Chile!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Background: we've been talking about taking a chunk of time off. Its a good time
for both Laura and I to take time off work, so now is the moment.  We were
talking about going to New Zealand and Australia, but we found photos of Patagonia on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.ie/search?q=patagonia&amp;hl=en&amp;safe=off&amp;prmd=imvns&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=4XiVUNC9N9SAhQeXyoDICw&amp;ved=0CAoQ_AUoAQ&amp;biw=1366&amp;bih=619&quot;&gt;internet&lt;/a&gt;, and our minds were set.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've away for 3 months, going to Chile and Argentina. We have a flight into
Santiago and another one out of Buenos Aires three months later. We'll see what
happens in between ;-).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're going to move out of our flat in Dublin - Its a nice place, but it needs
some work, and the only way that work will happen is if the landlord has to rent
it to some other sucker. We're going though all our stuff, sticking it in boxes,
and getting it in storage. Its remarkable how stuff accumulates if you aren't
moving all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've bought a tent, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/wade.david&quot;&gt;Dave&lt;/a&gt;. Its very nice, and weighs about nothing. We hauled it down to Galtymore, &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/photos/102479403334301156799/albums/5804324042094533681&quot;&gt;(see photos)&lt;/a&gt; where we froze to death. Worrying. It was well below freezing though.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've started packing stuff for the trip. Long long lists. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=yak%20shaving&quot;&gt;yak shaving&lt;/a&gt; goes on forever. We've spent tons of time on the internet, looking at photos and blogs and reports. This is why we have started this thingo. Perhaps we'll be a warning to others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently we're down to a week and a bit before going. Doesn't feel like a
long time...&lt;/p&gt;






</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://nuttall.im/chile//first-aid</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://nuttall.im/chile//first-aid.html"/>
    <title>first aid</title>
    <updated>2012-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Pete and Laura Nuttall</name>
      <uri>http://nuttall.im/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;

Among the unnerving thing about this trip is the first aid kits. We've both done
lots of walking, and we've carried a first aid kit for much of that. However,
south america ups the ante with this stuff. we've bothgotten a spray of
vaccines, and we've spent time buying yet more stuff for first aid. There's
something weird about standing in the tiny tiny first aid section of boots,
going &quot;where are your eye patches? or your sutures? How am I going to keep
myself alive with hair products?&quot; Al least its not a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g3Zy0o5z1_c&quot;&gt;this level&lt;/a&gt; yet.
&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  

</feed>
